Forgiveness
Last autumn, a friend called me
and said he had big news.
He said that a mutual friend
had passed away.
The next day I received another call
saying, "Now that he passed away,
shouldn't you forgive him
and attend his funeral?"
The friend who had passed was
a son of a parent rep back in high school.
I was suspended indefinitely from
first grade of high school because of him.
Due to this, I had a hard time throughout
my entire high school years.
In a way I've grown a habit of perceiving
the world negatively since then.
To share the story :
When I entered high school,
a friend of mine was smoking cigarettes.
I asked to try one out of curiosity.
At that very moment,
the now-dead friend saw me smoking
in passing and made a comment.
This escalated into a big fight between
him and friends who offered me cigarettes.
I wasn't aware of
all this at the moment.
I only found out afterwards
when I was called by the teachers.
The friend claimed that
he tried to stop me
from smoking which led to the fight.
I was eventually suspended
and had a hard time
all throughout high school.
I attended a co-ed school, and was
slapped in front of girls by the teachers.
I was humiliated.
Even when I did well on exams,
I was accused of cheating.
Such experiences have made
me live life pessimistically.
So when thinking of going to
the funeral out of forgiveness,
I thought to myself, 'What good
is it after all these years?'
I think I've grown a habit of pessimism
from the very incident.
I'd like to know how to overcome this.
It would be good for you
to attend the funeral.
Not attending the funeral would indicate
that you're still hurt from the past.
Attending the funeral unwillingly
would hurt you more.
But willingly attending would
indicate you've healed.
(Questioner) I did not
attend the funeral.
Whether you attended the funeral
or not isn't important.
What's important is realizing
you're still hurt by having not gone.
This happened to you in high school,
that's 40 to 50 years ago.
And yet the pain still remains within you.
It still affects your outlook
in life to be pessimistic.
You're of a certain age now,
it's about time to heal your wounds.
Whether you do or don't
doesn't necessarily affect you
in terms of monetary gain or loss.
But forgiving someone before you die
is about healing your own wounds.
If you think about it, the turn of events
all happened coincidentally.
The friend simply commented
on your smoking.
He only said you shouldn't smoke.
You were simply smoking
because you wanted to.
Your friend simply
commented out of his conviction.
Your other friends simply told him
to mind his own business.
(Sunim) Hence they
ended up fighting.
(Sunim) As the fight grew bigger,
teachers were informed.
As the teachers were informed,
they asked what had happened.
As they were told the story,
they asked who smoked.
As you had smoked,
you were suspended.
Smoking a single cigarette isn't
necessarily worth a severe punishment.
But the incident snowballed into
a physical fight, hence the suspension.
(Questioner) To this day,
I feel it was unfair.
Then how would have your friend felt?
He simply told you not to smoke and
got beaten up for it. How unfair is that?
Wouldn't he feel that way?
He didn't do anything wrong,
he only said you shouldn't smoke.
He didn't even smoke himself,
he just said you shouldn't.
And yet he got beaten up,
so he fought back.
He would've thought to himself,
'What did I do wrong?'
I only said students shouldn't smoke,
why was that a problem?
They should've admitted to their fault.
From his standpoint,
he'd think 'What's there to argue?'
Meanwhile you'd have
your own standpoint.
The incident happened
because of differences in perspectives.
As you age and study the dharma,
you should now be thinking :
While it caused me great pain,
it wasn't that big of a thing
when I reflect back on it.
I smoked a cigarette,
he told me not to.
Friends told him to mind
his own business.
Hence he felt it was unfair
and pointed out my wrongdoings
by stating the rules as is.
This provoked a physical fight.
Teachers found out,
they simply had to act upon it.
Hence it became a big incident.
It's essentially the same story as this :
Let's say you dropped a lit match
on the street while smoking.
You only dropped a match,
and yet it resulted in a huge fire
worth millions in damage.
If you're forced to
compensate for the millions,
wouldn't you feel it's unfair?
You'd think to yourself,
"What did I do so wrong?
I only dropped a match.
How did I cause so much damage?"
(Sunim) Things happen in life
irrespective of your intentions.
(Sunim) It's ultimately
nobody's fault that
(Sunim) things happened the way
they did for you.
(Sunim) It's not your friend's fault.
"But it still is", you would say.
"It's easy for you to say,
but I'm only human",
you'd say while objecting.
Someone said
the very thing yesterday.
We use 'being human'
as an excuse.
But to be holding on to
your suffering, whose loss is it?
(Questioner) It's my loss.
If you think back on it, it's not
necessarily your friend's fault.
(Questioner) Then
what about my teachers?
(Questioner) All those teachers
that hated me?
The teachers punished you
because you smoked.
(Questioner) But even after then...
You smoked and
caused a big incident.
Hence they branded you
as a troublemaker.
When a troublemaker
gets good grades,
their prejudice would make them
think he must have cheated.
(Sunim) Once a mistake is made,
it leads to prejudice and assumptions.
You're branded, you're
on a 'blacklist' so to speak.
Once you're branded,
that reputation follows you around.
It does feel unfair,
but that is life.
(Sunim) With that one incident,
your bad reputation followed you around.
You could've tried
redeeming yourself,
yet you held a grudge and continued
your wrongdoings. Hence the cycle went on.
It's not too late to stop and
think instead, "I had it all wrong.
I was young and foolish, I didn't know."
By thinking this way,
you heal your own wounds.
(Questioner) Yes, I understand.
(Sunim) You see, the world
is full of victims.
And yet the offenders hardly
even remember what they had done.
If they caused 10,
they hardly remember 1.
Meanwhile in a victim's mind,
10 becomes magnified to 100.
You still feel mistreated and misjudged
to this day, and yet what do others say?
They'd say,
"You're in your 60s and yet still
fussing over it all these years?"
And what does that make you?
It makes you look petty.
(Questioner) I was foolish.
In Korean tradition, we say that even
the deepest grudges should be resolved
when a person passes.
Do we not?
(Sunim) In the same context, you're
approaching death yourself, are you not?
It's better to resolve
these issues for yourself.
(Questioner) I will repent before I die.
Although the pain you feel runs deep,
objectively speaking,
it was a small thing that happened
You've blown up a speck of dust
into a mountain and held onto it.
You see it as a mountain now.
But once you let go,
you'll realize it's a speck of dust.
Repenting doesn't necessarily mean
that you did something wrong.
It means realizing that it's wrong
to hold onto your pain and grudge.
You didn't hurt anyone after all.
(Questioner) Yes, I understand.
Thank you.